After tax economic analysis
subject of this chapter
What we want to see is what is the impact of tax on our business
So far we've done before tax analysis
now we want to do an after tax analysis
As you will see the only difference between the two is the tax
it's not that we for a replacement, an after tax replacement for instance
will have a totally new approach or method that is not anything like the one we had when we did not consider tax
So only difference will be the tax
Let's have a look at the terminology
By the way, of course, taxes are real cash flows
You will see that we use depreciation in computing our taxes
but these depreciations are only used for computing our taxes, they are not cash flows
So what is important is that we know our net operating income
which are gross revenues minus our operating expenses
Gross revenue, gross income represented by GIOE for our operating expenses
we have been encountering that one before
Taxable income is then the gross revenue minus our operating expenses
This one, sorry, this is this
but also we can deduct our depreciation
so that means that the taxable income becomes lower
What else do I need to say?
I think that then what are the taxes?
The taxes are then your tax rate times your taxable income
and your net profit X after taxes obviously is then our taxable income minus our taxes
Tax rates, I already hinted to it when we talked about depreciation and taxes in the previous chapter
In some countries we have different tax levels
We have a local tax level for instance for a state or a province
and there are federal rates and we have to make one tax rate out of that
and that's what we are going to do
We are only going to look at effective tax rates here
What you see to the right, the table is not recent
That's what was mentioned in the book
But what it's illustrating is that tax rates can be quite different from country to country
and although this is out of scope of this course
it's good to mention that taxes can be an important argument for companies to start a production plant
in a given country for instance or to locate their headquarters in another country
So it's an important aspect but we will not pursue that in this course
Let's have our cash flow before taxes
Cash flow before taxes is gross income or revenues minus operating expenses
minus any investment plus any salvage value that there might be
And after taxes we have this amount
We have as we saw before
We have of course this before
But then we have our taxes that we have to deduct
and the taxes that we have to deduct or determined by our gross income, operating expenses
and also by our depreciation
Now what about the effect of taxes
What about the effect on taxes by the depreciation method and the recovery method
Well as you see here all methods, all depreciation methods will lead to the same amount of total taxes
and here also all lengths will have the same amount of total taxes
But what is important of course is the present worth of the taxes
Now let's have an example
So this is an example about a Mexican manufacturing company
It's a multinational and they are also active in Germany
The company just purchased an asset for 90,000 with an estimated useful life of 9 years
However the German tax law allows a shorter recovery period, namely of 5 years
Their net income is 30,000 per year
and now we are asked to demonstrate the tax advantage for the shorter period
5 years instead of 9 years
with an effective tax rate of 35%
and if invested money is returning a 5% per year after taxes
We should not take into account any salvage value and a classic straight line depreciation is to be used
Let's have a look
So for 9 years straight line depreciation
we know that the amount of depreciation every year will be 90,000 divided by the number of years is 10,000
Taxable income is our income per year
Minus our operating expenses is 20,000
Taxable income is our income minus our depreciation
Tax rate times that taxable income is 7,000
and it's for every year that we have to consider that
So that means that the present worth of taxes will be 49,755
and the total of taxes that we have to pay, well every year we pay 7,000 so that's easy
That's 63,000
Now if we go to the other system with the shorter recovery period
We of course have the same formulas but now we have our depreciation for the first 5 years is 18,000
because we are allowed to have that accelerated depreciation
and we will have no depreciation for years 6 to 9
So our taxes will be the tax rate times our income minus our depreciation
4,200 for the first 5 years
and well we will have to pay on the full 30,000 for years 6 to 9
So the present worth of our taxes will be the 4,200
We pay the first 5 years, we have the 10,500
which we pay for the next years
and we make it a present worth as well
So here we have a present worth of 47,000
There we have a present worth of 49,755
The total taxes here was 63
Here the total taxes are 5 times the 10,500
and is again the 36,000 as was mentioned in the previous part